A Guide to the Records of the Policy Office of Governor James S. Gilmore, 1998-2001
Library of Virginia
- Series VII. Secretary of Public Safety, 1998-2001., Extent: 5 boxes. (Box 6-11)
  - Department of Military Affairs - State Military Reservation, 1998 (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Department of Military Affairs - Teko Williams, 1999 [RESTRICTED] (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Department of Military Affairs - Virginia National Guard Tuition Assistance, 1999 (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Parole Board - Abolition of Parole, 1994 (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Parole Board - Parole/Pardon Requests, 1998-2000 [RESTRICTED] (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Parole Board - Victim Rights Strategic Planning Group, 1998 (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Virginia State Police - 4-Safe-VA, 1999-2000 (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Virginia State Police - Governor Jim Gilmore's Partnership for School Safety: 4-Safe-VA, 1999 Briefing Book (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Virginia State Police - Governor Jim Gilmore's Partnership for School Safety: 4-Safe-VA Training Manuel (1999 August) (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Virginia State Police - Commonwealth v. Derek Rocco Barnabei, 2000 (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Virginia State Police - Chesterfield Grand Jury, 1998 (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Virginia State Police - Decision Briefs, 1998-2000 (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Virginia State Police - Executive Protection Unit, 1998 (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Virginia State Police - Fort Pickett Driver Training Facility, 1998 (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Virginia State Police - Helicopter, 1999-2000 (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Virginia State Police - Major Case/Report/Incident/Unusual Occurrence, 1998-2000 (2 copies) [RESTRICTED] (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Virginia State Police - Newport News Shipbuilding Strike, 1999 (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Virginia State Police - Notification of Criminal Investigations, 1998-2000 (2 copies) [RESTRICTED] (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Virginia State Police - Organized Crime in Solid Waste Industry, 1998 (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Virginia State Police - Pay Increase for State Troopers/Sheriffs, 1998 (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Virginia State Police - Statewide Communications-Land Mobiles, 1998-2000 (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Virginia State Police - Violent Crime Strike Forces, 1998-1999 (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Virginia State Police - Virginia Exile, 1998-1999 (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous - Virginia Exile Briefing Book for Governor Gilmore for United State House of Representatives Hearing on Project Exile, 2000 April 6 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous - Project Exile, Program Overview by United States Attorney's Office for the Eastern District of Virginia, 1998 September 27 (part one) (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous - Project Exile, Program Overview by United States Attorney's Office for the Eastern District of Virginia, 1998 September 27 (part two) (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous - Public Safety Response to Terrorism: Governor's Terrorism Consequence Management Briefing, ca. 1998 (Governor Gilmore's copy with notes) (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous - Public Safety Response to Terrorism: Governor's Terrorism Consequence Management Briefing, ca. 1998 (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous - Terrorism Consequence Management Plan by Virginia Department of Emergency Services, 1999 February (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous - Meeting Materials, Congressional Advisory Panel to Assess Preparedness for Weapons of Mass Destruction, Governor James S. Gilmore, III, Chairman, 1999 December 13, Santa Monica, California (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous - Meeting Materials, Congressional Advisory Panel to Assess Preparedness for Weapons of Mass Destruction, Governor James S. Gilmore, III, Chairman, 2000 September 28-29, Richmond, Virginia (part one) (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous - Meeting Materials, Congressional Advisory Panel to Assess Preparedness for Weapons of Mass Destruction, Governor James S. Gilmore, III, Chairman, 2000 September 28-29, Richmond, Virginia (part two) (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous - Second Annual Report of the Advisory Panel to Assess Domestic Response Capabilities for Terrorism Involving Weapons of Mass Destruction, 2000 December 15 (copy one) (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous - Second Annual Report of the Advisory Panel to Assess Domestic Response Capabilities for Terrorism Involving Weapons of Mass Destruction, 2000 December 15 (copy two) (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Series VIII. Secretary of Technology, 1999-2001., Extent: 31 folders. (Box 11)
  The Secretary of Technology series is housed in 32 folders. Notable files include: briefing books for Governor Gilmore's Las Vegas trip (8-9 January 1999) and Technology Mission to Washington State and California's Silicon Valley (19-21 April 1999 April).
  - Technology in the Economy - Established a Cabinet-Level Secretary of Technology, 1999-2001 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Technology in the Economy - Established Commission on Information Technology, 1999-2000 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Technology in the Economy - Virginia Internet Policy Act, 1999-2000 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Technology in the Economy - Advisory Commission on Electronic Commerce, 1998-2000 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Technology in the Economy - (VRTAC) Virginia Research and Technology Advisory Commission, 2000-2001 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Technology in the Economy - Commonwealth Technology Research Fund, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Technology in the Economy - Global Internet Summits, 1998-2000 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Technology in the Economy - World Congress on Information Technology, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Technology in the Economy - Main Street to E-Street Task Force, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Technology in the Economy - New Economy Legislation (UCITA & UETA), 2000 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Technology in the Economy - International Outreach, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Technology in the Economy - Virginia Link, 1999-2000 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Technology in the Economy - Telework! VA, 2000-2001 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Technology in Government - Council of Technology Services, 1998-2001 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Technology in Government - Electronic Government, 1999-2001 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Technology in Government - COVANET, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Technology in Government - COVITS, 1999-2001 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Technology in Government - Century Date Change Initiative (CDCI), 1999 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Technology in Society - E-Communities Task Force, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Technology in Society - Creating Digital Opportunities and Addressing the Digital Divide, 1999-2000 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Technology in Society - Mobile Learning Unit and Technotrain Projects, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Technology in Society - The Digital Dominion Web Site, 2000-2001 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Technology in Society - My Virginia, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous - Briefing Book for Governor Gilmore, Las Vegas Trip, 1999 January 8-9 (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous - Briefing Book for Governor Gilmore, Technology Mission to Washington State and California's Silicon Valley, 1999 April 18-21 (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous - Program, 1998 World Congress on Information Technology, George Mason University, 1999 June 21-24 (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous - Briefing Book for Governor Gilmore, Global Internet Summit, George Mason University, 2000 March 12-14 (Chris Whyte's copy - Director of Scheduling) (Box 11, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous - Briefing Book for Governor Gilmore, Global Internet Summit, George Mason University, 2000 March 12-14 (Mark Miner's copy - Press Secretary) (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous - Briefing and Agenda of E-Commerce Advisory Commission on Electronic Commerce Meeting, 1999 September 14-15, New York City, New York (Scheduling Office copy) (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous - Briefing and Agenda of E-Commerce Advisory Commission on Electronic Commerce Meeting, 1999 December 14-15, San Francisco, California (Scheduling Office copy) (Box 11, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous - Office of the Governor, Agency Contingency Plan for the Y2K Boundary Period, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous brochure, nd (Box 11, Folder 34)
- Series IX. Secretary of Transportation, 1998-2001., Extent: 41 folders. (Box 11-13)
  The Secretary of Transportation series is housed in 41 folders and is arranged alphabetically by state agency followed by briefing books. Agencies include: Department of Aviation, Department of Motor Vehicles, Department of Rail and Public Transportation, and Department of Transportation.
  Notable files under the Department of Aviation include: records on the Aviation World's Fair 2003, 2000-2001.
  Notable files under the Department of Motor Vehicles include: Personal Property Tax Relief Act of 1998 (car tax) including summary of meetings between Secretary of Transportation/Department of Motor Vehicles staff and the Governor's Office held between May 1998 and May 1999 concerning implementation of the Personal Property Tax Relief Act (copy also found in Secretary of Transportation's records - accession 38991).
  Notable files under the Department of Transportation include: I-895 (Pocahontas Parkway), 1997-1999; Route 288, 1999-2001; Springfield Interchange, 1996-2001; and the Woodrow Wilson Bridge, 1999-2001.
  Notable files under Briefing Books include: "Governor's Update: VDOT's Cash Position," 31 March 1999; Governor Gilmore's notes from VDOT meetings, 10-11 May 1999; "Transportation Concerns," August 1999 and Proposal to Acquire the Main Street Station by the City of Richmond, 6 December 1999.
  - Department of Aviation - Airport Revolving Fund, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 35)
  - Department of Aviation - Aviation World's Fair 2003, 2000-2001 (part one) (Box 11, Folder 36)
  - Department of Aviation - Aviation World's Fair 2003, 2000-2001 (part two) (Box 11, Folder 37)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles - Personal Property Tax Relief Act (Car Tax), 1998 (Box 11, Folder 38)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles - Personal Property Tax Relief Act (Car Tax), 1999 (Box 11, Folder 39)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles - Personal Property Tax Relief Act (Car Tax), 2000 (Box 11, Folder 40)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles - Personal Property Tax Relief Act (Car Tax), 2001 (Box 11, Folder 41)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles - Personal Property Tax Relief Act (Car Tax), Summary of Meetings at Governor's Office on Personal Property Tax Relief, 1998-1999 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles - Personal Property Tax Relief Act (Car Tax), Policy Decisions and Guidance from the Attorney General, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles - Personal Property Tax Relief Act (Car Tax), Auditor of Public Accounts Legislative Study, 2000 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles - Personal Property Tax Relief Act (Car Tax), Articles and Press Releases, 1998-2001 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Department of Rail and Public Transportation - Eastern Shore Railroad, 1998-2001 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Department of Rail and Public Transportation - High Speed Rail, 1996-2001 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Department of Rail and Public Transportation - Mag Lev Demonstration Project, 1998-2001 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Department of Rail and Public Transportation - Main Street Station, 1997-2000 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Department of Rail and Public Transportation - Washington/Richmond Rapid Rail, 1999-2000 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Department of Transportation - I-895 (Pocahontas Parkway), 1997-1999 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Department of Transportation - Route 288, 1999-2001 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Department of Transportation - Springfield Interchange, 1996-2001 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Department of Transportation - Virginia Maintenance Services (VMS), 1996-2001 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Department of Transportation - Western Transportation Corridor, 1997-1998 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Department of Transportation - Woodrow Wilson Bridge, 1999-2001 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - General - Governor's Commission on Transportation Policy, 1999 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - General - Governor's Commission on Transportation Policy, 1999-2000 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - General - Governor's Commission on Transportation Policy, 2001 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - General - GARVEE Legislation, 1999-2000 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - General - Innovative Progress Priority Transportation Initiative, 2000 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Briefing Books/Reports - Virginia Department of Transportation, Transition Book, prepared for the Secretary of Transportation, 1998 January 7 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Briefing Books/Reports - National Capital Region Congestion and Mobility Summit, Washington, D.C., 1998 May 28, Briefing Material (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Briefing Books/Reports - Commonwealth Transportation Board: Six Year Improvement Program, Fiscal Year 1998-99, Volume 1 (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Briefing Books/Reports - Commonwealth Transportation Board: Six Year Improvement Program, Fiscal Year 1998-99, Volume 2 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Briefing Books/Reports - Governor's Transportation Briefing, 1999 January (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Briefing Books/Reports - Governor's Update: VDOT's Cash Position, 1999 March 31 & Governor Gilmore's notes from VDOT meetings 1999 May 10-11 (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Briefing Books/Reports - Transportation Concerns, 1999 August (copy one) (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Briefing Books/Reports - Transportation Concerns, 1999 August (copy two) (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - Briefing Books/Reports - Innovative Progress: Improving Transportation in Northern Virginia, 1999 August 31 (copy one) (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - Briefing Books/Reports - Innovative Progress: Improving Transportation in Northern Virginia, 1999 August 31 (copy two) (Box 12, Folder 30)
  - Briefing Books/Reports - Innovative Progress: Improving Transportation in Northern Virginia, 1999 August 31 (copy three) (Box 12, Folder 31)
  - Briefing Books/Reports - Proposal to Acquire the Main Street Station, by the City of Richmond, 1999 December 6 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Briefing Books/Reports - Second Interim Report: The Governor's Commission on Transportation Policy, 2000 September 14 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Briefing Books/Reports - Commission on Transportation Policy Recommendations/Work Plans, 2001 March 21 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Series X. Miscellaneous, 1998-2001., Extent: 16 folders. (Box 13-14)
  The Miscellaneous series is housed in 16 folders and is arranged chronologically. Notable files include: briefing book on Procurement Assessment Task Force, ca. 1999; and Constituent Contact Procedures manual, November 1999.
  - Program for The Marshall Leadership Program for the Commonwealth of Virginia, 1998 August 6-8, Lexington, Virginia (copy one) (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Program for The Marshall Leadership Program for the Commonwealth of Virginia, 1998 August 6-8, Lexington, Virginia (copy two) (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Program for 1998 Governor's Executive Leadership Workshop, 1998 September 9 (part one) (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Program for 1998 Governor's Executive Leadership Workshop, 1998 September 9 (part two) (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Copy of Building Virginia's Future: A Time for All Virginias, A Strategic Plan for the Commonwealth of Virginia, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Briefing Book on Procurement Assessment Task Force, ca.1999 (part one) (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Briefing Book on Procurement Assessment Task Force, ca.1999 (part two) (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Visitor Service Facilities Plan prepared by Visitor Facilities Task Force, 1999 November 3 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Constituent Contact Procedures manual, 1999 November (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Media Briefing Book, 1999 August (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Media Briefing Book[?], 1999 September (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - General Assembly Notebook, 2000 Session (part one) (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - General Assembly Notebook, 2000 Session (part two) (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - General Assembly Notebook, 2001 Session (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Memorandum to John Mahone from Bruce Jamerson, Clerk of the House of Delegates, 2000 June 14, on Funding for Pressroom Renovation (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - 1998 Special Session Budget (Box 13, Othertype Publication)
  - Albert Arnold Gore, Jr. On the Issues, 1999 April (Box 13, Othertype Publication)
  - CSG State Directory, Administrative Officials, 1998 (Box 13, Othertype Publication)
  - CSG State Directory, Legislative Leadership, Committees and Staff, 1999 (Box 14, Othertype Publication)
  - Public Relations Tactics - The Blue Book, 1999/2000 (Box 14, Othertype Publication)
- Series XI. Records of Lee E. Goodman, 1998-2001., Extent: 18 folders. (Box 14)
  This series consists of the records of Lee E. Goodman, Special Counsel to the Governor, Deputy Counselor and Deputy Chief of Policy for Governor Gilmore. The series is housed in 18 folders and is arranged alphabetically by subject followed by miscellaneous material. Notable files include: Goodman's files on the car tax including constitutional amendments and lawsuits: Freedom of Information Act requests; Governor's Emergency Powers (9/11); miscellaneous correspondence; University of Virginia Balcony cases; University of Virginia-Qatar; and the appointment of Gibson, Dunn and Crutcher as VDOT special counsel. Note many of these records are restricted either because of attorney-client privilege or executive privilege.
  - No Car Tax/Personal Property Tax Relief Act of 1998 (part one) (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - No Car Tax/Personal Property Tax Relief Act of 1998 (part two) (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - No Car Tax/Personal Property Tax Relief Act of 1998 (part three) (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Car Tax - Constitutional Amendment, 2000-2002 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Car Tax Lawsuit, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Freedom of Information Act (FOIA)Requests, 1998-2000 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Freedom of Information Act (FOIA)Requests, 2000 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Freedom of Information Act (FOIA)Requests, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Governor's Emergency Powers/Legal (9/11), 2001 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1997-2001 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Special Counsel Appointments, 1998-2001 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - University of Virginia Balcony Cases/Settlements, 1998-1999 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - University of Virginia - Qatar, 1998-1999 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Department of Transportation/Gibson, Dunn and Crutcher, 1999-2001 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous - Remarks by Governor Jim Gilmore, News Conference on Terrorism, National Press Club, 2001 September 17 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous - Testimony of Governor James S. Gilmore, Hearing of the U.S. Senate Committee on Government Affairs, 2001 September 21 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous - Testimony of Governor James S. Gilmore, Hearing of U.S. House of Representatives Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence, Subcommittee on Terrorism and Homeland Security, 2001 September 26 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous - Testimony of Governor James S. Gilmore, Hearing of U.S. House of Representatives Committee on Science, 2001 October 17 (Box 14, Folder 18)
- Series XII. Policy Analysis, 1998., Extent: 1 folder. (Box 14)
  This series consists of one policy analysis from 5 August 1998 and is restricted per the Gilmore-Library of Virginia agreement.
  - Policy Analysis, 5 August 1998 (RESTRICTED) (Box 14, Folder 19)